Finding Aid for the Alan Le May Papers LSC.0880
UCLA Library Special Collections
Alan Le May papers
1940-1963
UCLA Library Special Collections
Le May, Alan
LSC.0880
11.5 Linear Feet (23 boxes)
Alan Le May (1899-1964) began his career as a journalist and author of westerns, some of which were adapted to the screen. He also produced a number of short stories and screenplays in addition to 17 novels. The collection contains manuscripts of novels, story outlines, and screenplays for television and motion pictures by Le May.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Arlene Le May, 1964.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9919730973606533
Biography
Alan Le May was born June 3, 1899 in Indianapolis, Indiana; attended Stetson University and University of Chicago (Ph.B., 1922); began career as journalist; author of westerns, some of which were adapted to the screen, including The Searchers (1954) and The Unforgiven (1957); he was a prolific writer, producing a number of short stories and screenplays in addition to 17 novels; produced and directed High Lonesome in 1950; died on April 27, 1964.
Scope and Content
Collection contains manuscripts of novels, story outlines, and screenplays for television and motion pictures by Le May. Also includes correspondence and ephemera.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Manuscripts (Boxes 1-21).
Research materials (Boxes 2, 22).
Personal papers (Box 23).
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Screenplays; Television plays.; Screenwriters -- United States -- Archives.; Le May, Alan, 1899-1964--Archives.
- Manuscripts:
  - African Pitfall. Original story treatment. Pacific Palisades., n.d. (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Included are 5 copies, typescript and carbon. This is an outline of a story, with research information.
  - Angels Camp. n.p., 1949.; Manuscript and typescript. (Box 1)
    This is a draft of a story, with plans and notes.
  - Black Cat Patrol. Screenplay. California, ca., 1951. (Box 1)
    Included are 4 mimeograph copies, in manila folders.
  - The Blond in the Box Stall. n.p., Typescript. (Box 1)
    Story frame.
  - Boom Camp Printer. Story subject for The Virginian, a television series. n.p., n.d.; Typescript and carbon. 4 copies with a few corrections. (Box 2)
  - Calamity Jane. Screenplay. n.p., October 14, 1944.; Typescript (carbon). (Box 2)
  - , vol.1 & 2. Research notes on the South and the Civil War., 1862; Typescript. Each volume bound in maroon paper cover, and filed in a manila folder. (Box 2)
    There is no indication as to when this work was done, but perhaps it was undertaken in conjunction with working on the Civil War Story, eventually titled By Dim and Flaring Lamps.
  - Fort Cloud. n.p., n.d.; Typescript. (Box 2)
    Story idea.
  - FSO series. n.p., n.d.; Typescript. (Box 2)
    Story idea and plan for a series of screenplays.
  - Project Hotspot. n.p., 1962.; Typescript and carbons. 8 copies, with corrections. (Box 2)
    This is an outline and plan for a possible series of films.
  - Hardship Post. Screenplay. Story outline, incomplete script. n.p., n.d.; Typescript and carbon. Filed in manila folders. (Box 3)
  - I'd Rather Be Dead Than Fourteen; and Other Stories. n.p., April 1963.; Typescript, some carbon. (Box 3)
    Included is an outline for a series of stories, and a ninety-minute story plan for I'd Rather Be Dead Than Fourteen.
  - Brickyard. A one hour teleplay. n.p. Typescript, some carbon., n.d.; Typescript, some carbon. Filed in manila folders. (Box 4)
    Included are various versions, with extensive corrections, and note cards. The leaves are not in any particular order.
  - By Dim and Flaring Lamps. [New York]., Typescript, some carbon. (Box 5, Box 6, Box 7)
    Included are many typescript leaves, notes, revised and corrected versions. The leaves are filed in manila folders, in no particular order. The novel is about the South and the Civil War.
  - Civil War Story. n.p., n.d.; Typescript, much carbon. (Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12)
    Included are many typescript leaves, notes, and revised and corrected versions of a story that was later to become By Dim and Flaring Lamps. Research material is also included.
    Many of the leaves are filed in manila folders, in no particular order. Other leaves are grouped in small boxes.
  - The Maharajah. n.p., ca., 1963.; Typescript, some carbon. (Box 13)
    Included is the story treatment of the screenplay, the screenplay itself, and correspondence and notes relating to the work.
  - The Night Riders. n.p., n.d.; Typescript, some carbon. (Box 14)
    This appears to be another version of the Civil War Story that later became By Dim and Flaring Lamps.
    Included are various notes, and typescript leaves of the novel.
  - The Night Riders. n.p. (Later to become By Dim and Flaring Lamps.)., Typescript (carbon). (Box 15)
  - Passport. n.p., n.d.; Typescript (carbon) and photostat. (Box 15)
  - Passport. n.p., n.d.; Typescript, some carbon. Filed in manila folders. (Box 16)
    This is a prospectus for a television series, and related drafts, and other materials. Many versions and revised leaves.
    General note
    Some of the material is filed in a small box in Box 15 of the collection.
  - Old Man Coffee Stories. n.p., n.d.; Typescript (carbon). (Box 17)
    Included is a story plan, and one 24-minute screenplay entitled An Old Man Coffee Story.
  - Omaha. n.p., July 1963.; Typescript, some carbon. (Box 17)
    This is a screenplay, possibly for a series on television.
    The leaves are filed in manila folders.
  - The Pitch Wagon. n.p., June 25, 1945.; Typescript. (Box 17)
    This apparently is a synopsis, and sequence rundown for a screenplay. Included are photos of actors and actresses clipped and pasted on sheets.
  - Short short story plots. n.p., n.d.; Typescript. (Box 17)
  - Thirty-five American action subjects. n.p., n.d.; Mimeograph. (Box 17)
    (Perhaps used in research for a series, or story)
  - Twenty-three epics. n.p., n.d.; Typescript (carbon). (Box 17)
  - Trumpet. n.p., n.d.; Typescript, some carbon. (Box 18)
    This is a screenplay, 4 copies, 3 different versions, with corrections, and revisions.
  - Taras Bulba. n.p., n.d.; Typescript, some carbon. (Box 19)
    This is a screenplay, and includes character sketches, and outlines, rough draft.
  - The Unforgiven. New York., n.d.; Typescript, mostly carbon, with extensive corrections. Filed in manila folders. (Box 19)
  - Weapons. n.p., n.d.; 2 notebooks. Filed in manila folders. (Box 19)
    The notebooks consist of clipped pictures of various weapons, and commentary, pasted on sheets of paper (Probably used as research material).
  - The Wide Country. California., 1962.; Typescript. (Box 20)
    Included are: I Was Hanged in Effigy, and 2 copies of Straight-Jacket for an Indian.
    It appears that The Wide Country is the title of a television series.
  - The Wide Country. Memory of a Filly. [California]., 1962.; Typescript, much carbon. (Box 21)
  - Wyoming. [California]. This appears to be story plans, or outlines., 1963.; Typescript and carbons. (Box 21)
- Research materials. (Box 22)
  Television Schedules.
- Correspondence, ephemera, and personal papers (financial reports)., Filed in manila folders. (Box 23)